This XML file does not appear to have any style information associated with it. The document tree is shown below.
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="https://sebbari.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
<link href="https://sebbari.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
<updated>2021-09-29T10:26:54+00:00</updated>
<id>https://dmws2021.github.io/feed.xml</id>
<title type="html">Data management workshop 2021</title>
<subtitle>Data management workshop 2021</subtitle>
<author>
<name>Athanassios Argiriou</name>
</author>
<entry>
<title type="html">IHT 2021</title>
<link href="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2021/iht2021/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IHT 2021"/>
<published>2021-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2021-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2021/iht2021</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2021/iht2021/"><p>We are excited to upload the revised version of our conference paper for the IHT 2021. The “12th National Conference for Renewable Energy Sources” is organized by the Institute of Solar Technology and will be held in Thessaloniki, Greece if the pandemic measures permit so.</p> <p>Our paper is focused at the results obtained in WP2 “Optical design and modeling of systems and tracking methods”. The optical simulation results obtained from two software packages on the “SCO1” configuration are discussed.</p> <p>The SCO1 system is based on a system studied theoretically and experimentally by Giannoulis and Tripanagnostopoulos at the Physics Department of the University of Patras, in Greece. The prototype consists of a static cylindro-parabolic concentrator and a flat absorber with a selective coating. The concentrator can be eitner symmetric (a) or a-symmetric (b,c).</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/sco1_old.png" alt="sco1_old" /></p> <p>SCO1 is an improved version of this system, where the absorber and can be enclosed in a vacuum tube and its surface can be treated with selective coating for improved efficiency. The absorber is tracking the concentrated sun rays either in a linear track or in a non linear one, aiming to take advantage of the of the higher concentration areas below.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/heatmap.png" alt="heatmap" /></p> <p>UPatras focused on extracting the optimal equation of motion for the absorber, while SIJ investigated the concept of absorber movement out of the system’s axis of symmetry.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/abs_movement.png" alt="heatmap" /></p> <p>The results of both software packages are in agreement with each other for the same test cases, while the inclined movement shows improved overall performance. As a conclusion, the SCO1 system has an improved efficiency compared to the older system version.</p></content>
<author>
<name>["Orestis Panagopoulos"]</name>
</author>
<category term="Conferences"/>
<summary type="html">We are excited to upload the revised version of our conference paper for the IHT 2021. The “12th National Conference for Renewable Energy Sources” is organized by the Institute of Solar Technology and will be held in Thessaloniki, Greece if the pandemic measures permit so.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title type="html">EuroSun 2020</title>
<link href="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2020/eurosun2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EuroSun 2020"/>
<published>2020-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2020-09-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2020/eurosun2020</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2020/eurosun2020/"><p>As everyone affected by the latest measures for the pandemic, the EuroSun 13th International Conference on Solar Energy for Buildings and Industry was not hosted in Athens, Greece as planned, but on a specifically designed web platform. Nevertheless, we did not miss the opportunity to showcase our work. <!-- The submitted paper was presented by Mr. Panagopoulos on behalf of the SCoSCo team. --></p> <p>Within the scope of the project in order to reduce costs, a concentrating collector with a simple flat-plate receiver is proposed. The optical concentrator consists of an array of mirror facets placed in a box that protects the mirrors from wind loads and dirt. The innovative micro mirror box system has a built-in tracking mechanism, but the whole system is fixed. The solar concentrator consists of an array of mirror facets preconfigured to form a focal point at approximately 1.5 m</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/sco4.png" alt="sco4" /></p> <p>This concept presents the following advantages:</p> <ul> <li> <p>The point-focusing feature allows high concentration values of ~50 even with relatively large optical and tracking errors of about ± 10 mrad.</p> </li> <li> <p>Instead of expensive receiver tubes, a small non-evacuated flat-plate receiver can be used.</p> </li> <li> <p>A patent of micro-mirror systems was filed by SIJ/DLR in 2006 (Sauerborn, 2008). A prototype developed for CSP applications was already designed.</p> </li> <li> <p>It is an innovative concept that has not yet been analysed and tested and no research results regarding its performance were found in the literature.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Raytracing models were created with the COMSOL (Fig.2) and Tonatiuh software tools. These calculations allow the specification of the number of mirrors, their dimensions, and their gap width.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/ray_tracing.png" alt="ray_tracing" /></p> <p>The angular ray distribution of the sun disk is also implemented on the mirror surfaces and combined with the optical error calculation.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/flux_analysis.png" alt="flux_analysis" /></p> <p>The complete model of the solar collector system for the calculation of annual energy yield with Matlab Simulink Carnot toolbox is shown below. The Carnot program combines the easy-to-use graphical environment of Simulink with the powerful algorithms and differential equation solvers of MATLAB for the application of solar thermal system simulation</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/thermal.png" alt="thermal" /></p> <p>The expected energy yield can be up to about 800 kWh/m²a under the weather conditions of Patras, Greece using standard optical components. Further improvements are possible by using AR glazing for the glass cover of the mirror array, higher absorber, or mirror quality. A cost-benefit analysis of these material properties will have to be carried out. The new collector design can also be integrated in buildings very easily. On our next steps, two identical prototypes will be assembled and tested experimentally in Jülich, Germany and Patras, Greece, in order to study the proposed system’s behaviour under outdoor conditions for both climate zones. Technical details of the tracking system, as well as operating problems and impacts on the overall system costs is confidential at this point but will be published as soon as the experimental testing is complete.</p></content>
<author>
<name>["Orestis Panagopoulos"]</name>
</author>
<category term="Conferences"/>
<summary type="html">As everyone affected by the latest measures for the pandemic, the EuroSun 13th International Conference on Solar Energy for Buildings and Industry was not hosted in Athens, Greece as planned, but on a specifically designed web platform. Nevertheless, we did not miss the opportunity to showcase our work.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title type="html">German-Greek Workshop on Knowledge and Technology Transfer</title>
<link href="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2019/athens-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="German-Greek Workshop on Knowledge and Technology Transfer"/>
<published>2019-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2019/athens-workshop</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2019/athens-workshop/"><p>Recently, we were glad to attend a two-day Workshop, hosted at NCSR DEMOKRITOS in Athens, Greece. The workshop implemented a training approach for awareness-raising and empowerment of existing German-Greek research projects. Keynotes on knowledge transfer and exercises provided the opportunity to gain practical experience and hone our skills on knowledge transfer. SIJ was represented by Prof. Alexopoulos, and UPatras by Mr Panagopoulos. Calpak’s Mr. Sfinias participated as well.</p> <h5 id="tuesday">Tuesday</h5> <p>On day 1, after being welcomed by the Greek Alternate Minister for Education, Research and Religious Affairs and the German Parliamentary State Secretary to the Federal Minister of Education and Research, we were guided through the Greek and German perspectives on our bilateral cooperation agreement. The overview, expectations and goals of the Greek-German Research and Innovation Program were presented by Dr. Maria Christoula of GSRT and Gisela Cramer von Clausbruch of BMBF. The day ended with us being received upon invitation of the BMBF at the residence of the German Ambassador in Athens, where we had the opportunity to exchange ideas with partners in a warm and friendly atmosphere.</p> <h5 id="wednesday">Wednesday</h5> <p>On day 2, Dr. Hans-Peter Niller of DLR outlined an overview of the Greek-German Research and Innovation Programme, while Manuel Molina Vogelsang of Fraunhofer IMW briefed us on strategic networking to enhance knowledge and technology transfer in international cooperation. With a common transfer vision was in mind as presented by Jördis Winkler of Fraunhofer IMW, the participants were separated in parallel working groups, based on project subject relevance. Our group, related to energy, was guided by Dr. Julian Kahl of Fraunhofer IMW. Other groups included Health &amp; Bio-Economy, Culture &amp; Tourism and Materials &amp; Key-Enabling Technologies. In the evening, Dr. Karen Böhme of PTJ aided us to summarize our findings, which were then showcased by 4 representatives of the working groups.</p> <h5 id="thursday">Thursday</h5> <p>On the last day, Dr. Karen Böhme summarized day 2 and provided an outlook on our tasks in hand. Wojciech Roskiewicz of Fraunhofer IMW explained ways to transfer results from research to market, and we were split to our groups and got to work. At 11:45, Dr. Steffen Preissler of Fraunhofer IMW coordinated a panel discussion, were 4 representatives from our parallel group sessions summarized the sessions’ findings.</p> <p>Following up Manuel Molina Vogelsang of Fraunhofer IMW provided an outlook on the workshop, noting interesting findings, before being farewelled by Gisela Cramer von Clausbruch of BMBF and Dr. Maria Christoula of GSRT.</p> <p>This workshop, yielded significant results on the Greek-German cooperation and the progress of its research projects. We were provided the opportunity to exchange ideas and discuss technical details on our projects and get informed on similar projects, opening the fields for potential cooperation with other Greek and German research institutions and companies.</p> <p>After the end of the workshop, Prof. Alexopoulos and Mr. Panagopoulos briefed the project partners on the workshop’s findings and overall impressions.</p></content>
<author>
<name>["Orestis Panagopoulos"]</name>
</author>
<category term="Meetings"/>
<summary type="html">Recently, we were glad to attend a two-day Workshop, hosted at NCSR DEMOKRITOS in Athens, Greece. The workshop implemented a training approach for awareness-raising and empowerment of existing German-Greek research projects. Keynotes on knowledge transfer and exercises provided the opportunity to gain practical experience and hone our skills on knowledge transfer. SIJ was represented by Prof. Alexopoulos, and UPatras by Mr Panagopoulos. Calpak’s Mr. Sfinias participated as well.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title type="html">Kickoff meeting</title>
<link href="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2018/kickoff-meeting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kickoff meeting"/>
<published>2018-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
<updated>2018-10-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2018/kickoff-meeting</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="https://dmws2021.github.io/blog/2018/kickoff-meeting/"><p>Last Monday, after having participated in a few web meetings, we were finally able to meet in person at SCoSCo’s kickoff meeting in SIJ’s facilities. We were able to organize our work plan effectively, after having discussed a lot of interesting ideas on the implementation of our project.</p> <p>The present participants introduced themselves with relevant information about their endeavors and expertise. Prof. Alexopoulos introduced SIJ and its specific fields of work to the participants. Mr. Konstantinidis introduced Calpak, which has a long experience in producing low-temperature solar collectors. Calpak’s portfolio includes a range of different collector types (FPC,VTC), thermosiphonic systems, and water tanks. The company has a well-established distribution system and is holding several Solar Keymark certifications. Nowadays the company is building a new production site in Corinth including a warehouse, offices and an exhibition room. One of the SCoSCo prototypes will be used in conjunction with a double effect absorption chiller, to cool the exhibition room. The company Heliokon was introduced by Mr. Yousefpour.</p> <p>The objectives and the timetable of the project were presented and discussed. By mutual agreement, it was decided to shift the schedule by 3 months, due to delayed start in each country. After getting into detail on the prototypes working principle and construction, Mr Schorn gave us a tour at SIJ’s research facilities and presented to us the test rig that will be used for the outdoor experiments. Returning to the meeting room, a short workshop on CARNOT was organized by Dr Göttsche. CARNOT is a thermal simulations MATLAB toolkit designed for solar thermal systems and will be used on our project. Before the end of the first day, we visited the solar tower at SIJ, guided by Prof. Alexopoulos.</p> <p>On Thursday, Prof. Alexopoulos, Mr Yousefpour and Mr Panagopoulos attended the Greek-German Programme Meeting in Forschungszentrum, Jülich. Our project’s general idea and work plan was presented to the audience by Prof. Alexopoulos. We are looking forward to our next project meeting in Patras, Greece in April/May 2019.</p></content>
<author>
<name>["Orestis Panagopoulos"]</name>
</author>
<category term="Meetings"/>
<summary type="html">Last Monday, after having participated in a few web meetings, we were finally able to meet in person at SCoSCo’s kickoff meeting in SIJ’s facilities. We were able to organize our work plan effectively, after having discussed a lot of interesting ideas on the implementation of our project.</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
